Guide to the Robert Price Papers, 1930s-2012 (bulk 1958-1965) MS 3130
New-York Historical Society
Robert Price papers
1930s-2012 (bulk 1958-1965)
New-York Historical Society
Price, Robert, 1932-2016
MS 3130
8 Linear feet in 8 record cartons and 2 oversize folders.
Papers of attorney, businessman, and political strategist Robert Price (1932–2016), who successfully managed John V. Lindsay's election to U.S. Congress as the representative from New York's 17th district (1958), and subsequent reelections to the same seat (1960, 1962, 1964), as well as Lindsay's first run for mayor of New York City (1965). Under Lindsay, Price served as the youngest deputy mayor in New York history. Price also engineered the sole victory of Nelson A. Rockefeller's otherwise unsuccessful bids for the presidency—the Republican nomination of the 1964 Oregon primary. The collection contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, posters, flyers, ephemera, lapel pins and buttons, and other paraphernalia from each of the campaigns above, and includes material documenting Price's personal and business interests.
Access Restrictions
This collection may be stored offsite. To arrange to consult it, please go to www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Steven Price, June 2018.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in five series:
Series I. John V. Lindsay political campaigns, 1958–1971
Series II. Nelson A. Rockefeller political campaigns, 1961–1974
Series III. Other political activities & material, 1930s–2012
Series IV. Price professional, 1958–1990
Series V. Price personal, 1953–2003
Biographical / Historical
Robert Price was born in the Bronx, New York, on August 27, 1932, to Eastern European Jewish immigrants Solomon and Frances (Berger) Price. Robert graduated from Bronx High School of Science in 1950 and later attended New York University (A.B., 1953). After serving as corporal in the U.S. Army (1953–1955), Price married Margery Beth Weiner on December 18, 1955. They would have two children: Eileen Marcia Price (later Farbman), born 1960, and Steven Price, born 1962.
After marrying, Price worked as an assistant in the legal department of R. H. Macy & Company while attending Columbia University's School of Law. He took an LL.B. from Columbia in 1958 and passed the New York State bar that same year. He worked briefly (1958–1959) as a law clerk to Judge Archie Owen Dawson of the United States District Court, Southern District of New York, and as Assistant United States Attorney for the Southern District of New York (1959–1960), before forming a law partnership with Theodore R. Kupferman in 1960.
By then Price had entered the world of political strategy. In 1958 John V. Lindsay, who sought election to Congress as the representative from New York's 17th district (on Manhattan's Upper East Side, so-called the "Silk Stocking District" for its affluence), recruited Price from the New York Young Republican Club to manage his campaign. Lindsay won the election and three subsequent reelections to the same seat in 1960, 1962, and 1964.
In 1964 Lindsay "lent" Robert Price to New York Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller to manage the latter's bid for the Republican nomination for president. Through Price's skill, Rockefeller, who had been running fourth in the Oregon polls, won that state's May 15 primary, eliminating Henry Cabot Lodge Jr. from the race and suddenly becoming a threat to rival Barry Goldwater in the upcoming California primary. Rockefeller wished to retain Price for the duration, but Lindsay needed him for his own reelection to Congress in November 1964, and so refused Price's services to Rockefeller.
John Lindsay decided to run for Mayor of New York City in 1965, and once again tapped Robert Price to get him elected. This he did, and Lindsay became the City's 103rd mayor on January 1, 1966. In reward Lindsay appointed Price his deputy, making him, at thirty-three, the youngest deputy mayor in New York history. Although his tenure was brief—from January to November 1966—Price negotiated an end to the 13-day transit strike that met the Lindsay administration on its first day. Price also killed Robert Moses's ill-met proposal to build an 8-lane highway, the Lower Manhattan Expressway (LOMEX) through Little Italy and Soho to connect the Holland Tunnel with the Williamsburg and Manhattan bridges.
Robert Price effectively left politics in 1966, beginning work that year as Executive Vice President, then Director, of the Dreyfus Corporation, and Investment Officer for the Dreyfus Fund. Between 1969 and 1972 he was President then Chairman of the Board of Price Capital Corporation (later called Highland Capital Corporation). Next he served as Vice President and General Partner of Lazard Frères & Co., Investment Bankers, from 1972 through 1978. The following year he founded Price Communications Corporation, which, by 1985, owned and operated three television and eleven radio stations, and had purchased New York Law Journal. In 1992, with his son, Steven, Price founded PriCellular Corp., a rural cellular carrier. The company went public in 1994 and in 1998 was acquired by American Cellular Corp. for $1.4 billion.
Robert Price died in Manhattan on April 15, 2016, aged eighty-three. His son, the philanthropist Steven Price, is executive chairman of Townsquare Media, an American radio network and media company, and a minority owner of the Atlanta Hawks basketball team.
See Sam Roberts, "Robert Price, Strategist for Lindsay and Rockefeller, Dies at 83," New York Times, April 22, 2016.
Scope and Contents
The strength of the Robert Price Papers lies in the correspondence, newspaper clippings, posters, flyers, ephemera, lapel pins and buttons, and other paraphernalia from each of the political campaigns Price managed for John V. Lindsay: his initial run for Congress, as Representative from New York's 17th district in 1958, and reelections to the same seat in 1960, 1962, and 1964; and Lindsay's run for Mayor of New York City in 1965. (Price had effectively left politics for the business sphere by the time of Lindsay's bid for reelection in 1969, so he did not manage that campaign.) See Series I.
In 1964 Price engineered the sole victory of Nelson A. Rockefeller's otherwise unsuccessful bids for the presidency—the Republican nomination of the 1964 Oregon primary. The collection includes correspondence, newspaper clippings, flyers, ephemera, and other paraphernalia centered on Rockefeller's Oregon win, as well as his later service to Richard M. Nixon during Nixon's campaign for reelection in 1972. See Series II.
Robert Price's brief time as deputy mayor of New York City—from January to November, 1966—is represented by biographical press releases, some correspondence, and a few speeches. See Series III, which includes a wealth of campaign samples—e.g., ephemera, buttons, lapel pins, nail files, bumper stickers, and other paraphernalia—produced by public candidates other than John V. Lindsay or Nelson A. Rockefeller, from New York and elsewhere (see Box 4, Folders 2–17, and Box 8c). Of note is the program (with accompanying admission ticket) for the Democratic Party's 1962 fundraising gala at Madison Square Garden, where Marilyn Monroe infamously sang "Happy Birthday, Mr. President" to John F. Kennedy (see Box 4, Folder 13). Also in Series III is a portable, mechanical Shoup Voting Machine Corporation sample of the type of lever voting machine common at New York polling places before their replacement by electronic scanners (see Box 8d).
The collection provides spotty coverage of Robert Price's evolving professional career outside the political sphere, from his days as a law clerk serving Judge Archie Owen Dawson of United States District Court, Southern District of New York, to his law partnership with Theodore R. Kupferman, through his days with the Dreyfus Fund (investment firm) and Lazard Frères & Co. (investment bankers), and his own Price Capital Corporation and Price Communications Corporation. See Series IV.
Personal material--e.g., correspondence, tax and financial records, résumés, and newspaper compositions--of Robert Price and his wife, Margery, their daughter Eileen (Price) Farbman, and son, Steven Price, rounds out the collection. See Series V.
Buttons (information artifacts); Campaign management -- New York (State) -- New York.; Campaign paraphernalia.; Legislators -- United States.; Mayors -- New York (State) -- New York.; Nominations for office.; Political campaigns -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Political candidates -- New York (State) -- New York.; Presidential candidates -- United States.; Primaries.; Ephemera.; Letters (correspondence); Political posters.; Press clippings.; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet); Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979
- Series I. John V. Lindsay political campaigns, 1958-1971
  Scope and Contents
  Series I includes correspondence, newspaper clippings, posters, flyers, ephemera, lapel pins and buttons, and other paraphernalia from each of John V. Lindsay's campaigns to win a seat in the U.S. House of Representatives from New York's 17th district (1958, 1960, 1962, and 1964), and from his initial campaign (1965) to become Mayor of New York City.
  Arrangement
  Series I is divided in two chronologically organized sub-series:
  Sub-series I.A. Lindsay congressional campaigns, 1958–1964
  Sub-series I.B. Lindsay mayoral campaign & miscellaneous, 1965-1971
  - Sub-series I.A. Lindsay congressional campaigns, 1958-1964
    John V. Lindsay was a Republican member of the U.S. House of Representatives from New York's 17th district, in office January 3, 1959 – December 31, 1965. The 17th district corresponded to Manhattan's Upper East Side, an area derided by some as the "Silk Stocking District" for its affluence. Robert Price managed Lindsay's initial election campaign (1958) and each of his subsequent reelections (1960, 1962, and 1964). Series I.A includes material from each campaign, such as correspondence, newspaper clippings, posters, flyers, ephemera, lapel pins and buttons, and other paraphernalia.
    Material is organized chronologically.
    - 1958 Lindsay congressional campaign (elected November 4, 1958) [3 folders] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - 1960 Lindsay congressional campaign (reelected November 8, 1960) [6 folders], 1959-1960 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4-9)
    - 1962 Lindsay congressional campaign (reelected November 6, 1962) [4 folders], 1961-1962 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10-13)
    - 1964 Lindsay congressional campaign (reelected November 3, 1964 [5 folders], 1963-1964 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14-18)
    - 1958-1964 Lindsay congressional campaigns. Loose material. [6 folders] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-6)
    - 1958-1964 Lindsay congressional campaigns. Photographs (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1958-1964 Lindsay congressional campaigns. Balloons (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
      Orange, yellow, and blue balloons stamped in black "LINDSAY FOR CONGRESS."
      Restricted
      RESTRICTED due to deteriorated condition. Do not remove from protective enclosure.
    - 1958-1964 Lindsay congressional campaigns. Posters [6 items] (Oversize large)
      • ELECT / JOHN LINDSAY / [portrait] / REPUBLICAN CANDIDATE / FOR CONGRESS / VOTE ROW A [1 copy]
      • VOTE FOR / GOVERNOR ROCKEFELLER'S TEAM! / FOR CONGRESS - 17TH DISTRICT / JOHN LINDSAY / FOR CONGRESS - 19TH DISTRICT / RICHARD S. ALDRICH / FOR STATE SENATOR / JOSEPH PINTO / FOR ASSEMBLYMAN / PAUL J. CURRAN / VOTE ROW "A" ALL THE WAY [1 copy]
      • RE-ELECT / CONGRESSMAN JOHN V. / [portrait] / LINDSAY / OUTSTANDING PUBLIC SERVANT / VOTE ROW A [4 copies]
    - 1958-1964 Lindsay congressional campaigns. Buttons & lapel pins [20 items] (Offsite-box 8, Box 8a)
      • LINDSAY (gold lettering on red background; plastic) [10 copies]
      • LINDSAY (white lettering on blue background; metal) [1 copy]
      • Re-Elect Lindsay to Congress (small) [2 copies]
      • Re-Elect Lindsay to Congress (medium) [4 copies]
      • Back Up Lindsay Vote Column A on Election Day [2 copies]
      • I'M JOHN LINDSAY (black lettering on yellow background) [1 copy]
    - 1958-1964 Lindsay congressional campaigns. Medal [5 copies] (Offsite-box 8, Box 8a)
      • Obverse: image of U.S. Capitol surrounded by "17th CONGRESSIONAL DISTRICT NEW YORK / JOHN V. LINDSAY."
      • Reverse: "WITH APPRECIATION AND WARM REGARD" followed by facsimile signature "John V. Lindsay M.C."
    - 1958-1964 Lindsay congressional campaigns. Ball-point pens [19 items] (Offsite-box 8, Box 8a)
      • Blue and white ball-point pen with black text: "With Best Wishes / Congressman / John V. Lindsay / 17th Congressional District" [17 copies]
      • Gold tone ball-point pen with facsimile signature: "John V. Lindsay" [2 copies]
    - 1958-1964 Lindsay congressional campaigns. Ink stamp (Offsite-box 8, Box 8a)
      COMMITTEE FOR JOHN V. LINDSAY.
  - Sub-series I.B. Lindsay mayoral campaign & miscellaneous, 1965-1971
    John V. Lindsay served as the 103rd Mayor of New York City, in office January 1, 1966 – December 31, 1973. Price managed Lindsay's initial run for mayor in 1965. As a reward for the win, Lindsay appointed Price deputy mayor (at age 33 he was the youngest deputy mayor in the City's history). Price had effectively left politics for the business sphere by the time of the Lindsay's bid for reelection in 1969, so he was not involved with that campaign. Like Series I.A, Series I.B includes a mix of correspondence, newspaper clippings, posters, flyers, ephemera, lapel pins and buttons, and other paraphernalia.
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign (elected November 2, 1965) [10 folders] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9-18)
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. FCC complaint, 1965 September - November (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
      Robert Price alleged that station personnel at WNBC-TV, Channel 4, New York, committed prejudicial acts against John Lindsay's mayoral campaign. For instance, one Lindsay television spot lacked sound, but the commercial preceding it and a Beame advertisement following it were audible.
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Loose material [4 folders] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20-23)
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Periodical clippings [folder 1 of 7] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
      James M. Perry, "The New Politics: Selling Lindsay Retail," New York Magazine, April 29, 1965.
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Periodical clippings [folder 2 of 7] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
      • Warren Weaver Jr., "Big Gamble of John Vliet Lindsay," New York Times Magazine, May 23, 1965 [article torn from issue, but retains cover photograph of Lindsay].
      • Richard Armstrong, "Second Man at City Hall" [profile of Robert Price], New York Times Magazine, December 26, 1965.
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Periodical clippings [folder 3 of 7] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
      "Why the G.O.P. is Smiling Again: Lindsay is Running," LIFE, May 28, 1965.
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Periodical clippings [folder 4 of 7] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
      "GOP Hope--LINDSAY OF N.Y.," Newsweek, May 31, 1965.
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Periodical clippings [folder 5 of 7] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
      "Lindsay on the Line," Newsweek, July 12, 1965.
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Periodical clippings [folder 6 of 7] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
      Noel E. Parmentel Jr., "John V. Lindsay: Less Than Meets the Eye," Esquire, October [1965].
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Periodical clippings [folder 7 of 7] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
      "Why City Government Must be Nonpartisan," LOOK, October 19, 1965.
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Ephemera (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Balloons (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
      Orange, yellow, green, blue, and pink balloons stamped in black "LINDSAY FOR MAYOR."
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Dashboard placards & license plate covers [4 items] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
      • dashboard placards: OFFICIAL LINDSAY FOR MAYOR [2 copies]
      • license plate covers: LINDSAY FOR MAYOR [2 versions: neon orange & black; blue & white]
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Record album (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
      Vinyl, 33 & 1/3-RPM disc--"The Lindsay Record"--issued by Columbia Special Products. Side 1: "Everything's Coming Up Roses;" "Why Should it Be;" "What can I do for New York;" and "The Small Business People." Side 2: "Why I want to be mayor;" "What are we going to do for the City of New York." In a pictorial sleeve with Lindsay's portrait on front and his voting record on back.
      Until this record has been preservation reformatted, it may not be played. In any case, the New-York Historical Society lacks the required playback equipment. Researchers may consult the album sleeve for its information.
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Posters [4 items] (Oversize large)
      • Milton Mollen / FOR COMPTROLLER / [portrait] / Elect Lindsay/Mollen/Costello [1 copy]
      • Dirty air. / Dirty lungs. / Dirty laundry. / He'll do / something / about air pollution/ ELECT / JOHN / LINDSAY / MAYOR / Vote the Lindsay Team / Lindsay-Mollen-Costello [1 copy, on stiff cardboard]
      • "He is fresh and everyone else is tired." / VOTE FOR / JOHN LINDSAY / FOR MAYOR [full length portrait in two parts]
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Buttons & lapel pins [96 items] (Offsite-box 8, Box 8b)
      • The Best News Since La Guardia / Lindsay for Mayor / [Bob Price name tag] [1 copy]
      • DEMOCRATS FOR LINDSAY [1 copy]
      • IF LINDSAY WERE MAYOR I'D MOVE BACK TO NEW YORK [2 copies]
      • LINDSAY FOR MAYOR (blue lettering on white background; small) [44 copies]
      • LINDSAY FOR MAYOR (blue lettering on white background; medium) [4 copies]
      • LINDSAY FOR MAYOR (with portrait; small) [6 copies]
      • LINDSAY FOR MAYOR (with portrait; large) [5 copies]
      • LINDSAY FOR MAYOR STAFF [1 copy]
      • LINDSAY STAFF (gold pinback) [3 copies]
      • PARA / VIVA / LINDSAY / SI SI SI / ALCALDE [For / Life / Lindsay / Yes Yes Yes / Mayor] [9 copies]
      • PRESS / LINDSAY [5 copies]
      • RADIO / LINDSAY [4 copies]
      • TV / LINDSAY [1 copy]
      • STOP / THINK / GO / LINDSAY [10 copies]
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Buttons & lapel pins. Oversize (Offsite-box 8, Box 8d)
      Let's Clean-Up the Mess In Our City / Vote the LINDSAY Team / Linday for Mayor / Costello for President of the City Council / Mollen for Comptroller [1 copy]
    - 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign. Television spots (Offsite-box 8, Box 8c)
      One reel of 10mm [?] film labeled "4 JVL TV spots 10 seconds each":
      1. "Rundown Schools"
      2. "Looted Stores"
      3. "Air Pollution"
      4. "Slum Scene"
      See Box 2, Folder 19, for documentation of Robert Price's complaint to the FCC that WNBC-TV, Channel 4, New York, among other allegations of favoritism, deliberately sabotaged the airing of Lindsay's spots.
      Until this film has been preservation reformatted, it may not be played. In any case, the New-York Historical Society lacks the required playback equipment.
    - Lindsay miscellaneous, 1966-1971 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
      A small amount of Lindsay-related newspaper clippings and press releases dating from after Robert Price's time as Deputy Mayor. Includes a press release naming Robert W. Sweet as Price's successor.
- Series II. Nelson A. Rockefeller political campaigns, 1961-1974
  Series II includes correspondence, newspaper clippings, flyers, ephemera, and other paraphernalia centered on Rockefeller's 1964 Oregon primary victory, as well as his later service to Richard M. Nixon during Nixon's campaign for reelection in 1972.
  - Rockefeller. General, 1961-1963 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1964 Rockefeller Oregon Republican Presidential Primary (May 15, 1964) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1964 Rockefeller Oregon Republican Presidential Primary. Advertisements (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1964 Rockefeller Oregon Republican Presidential Primary. Canvassing [2 folders] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9-10)
    Includes telephone scripts and door-to-door canvasser's instruction sheets.
  - 1964 Rockefeller Oregon Republican Presidential Primary. Returned mailings (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
    Sixteen returned mailing envelopes (postmarked 21-22 April 1964), most still sealed, some empty, and a few open to reveal "Win With Rockefeller" brochures and a letter from William E. Walsh, State Chairman, Rockefeller for President Committee.
  - 1964 Rockefeller Oregon Republican Presidential Primary. Clippings [5 folders] (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12-16)
  - Rockefeller. Ephemera [3 folders], 1964 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17-19)
  - Rockefeller. Nixon re-election [2 folders], 1972 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20-21)
    Includes drafts of Rockefeller's speech nominating Richard M. Nixon at the Republican National Convention in Miami, August 22, 1972.
  - Rockefeller. General, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
  - Rockefeller material loaned to Cary Reich, 1964-1973 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23)
    Cary Reich (1949-1998) was the author of The Life of Nelson A. Rockefeller: Worlds to Conquer, 1908-1958 (New York: Doubleday, 1996). Includes a letter from Reich thanking Price for loan of the material.
- Series III. Other political activities & material, 1930s-2012
  Series III holds scant material from Robert Price's time as deputy mayor of New York City (January–November, 1966): biographical press releases, some correspondence, and a few speeches. Of interest for their rarity are the campaign samples—e.g., ephemera, buttons, lapel pins, nail files, bumper stickers, and other paraphernalia—produced by public candidates other than John V. Lindsay or Nelson A. Rockefeller, from New York and elsewhere (see Box 4, Folders 2–17, and Box 8c). Series III includes a program and ticket for the Democratic Party's 1962 fundraising gala at Madison Square Garden at which Marilyn Monroe infamously sang "Happy Birthday, Mr. President" to John F. Kennedy (see Box 4, Folder 13). Also in Series III is a portable, mechanical Shoup Voting Machine Corporation sample of the type of lever voting machine common at New York polling places before their replacement by electronic scanners (see Box 8d).
  Material is organized chronologically, except for the campaign samples, ephemera, and paraphernalia, which are grouped after the topic-specific folders.
  - Republican Club of the 9th Assembly District, 1957-1963 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24)
  - Deputy Mayor. Biographical, 1965 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
  - Deputy Mayor. Correspondence, 1966 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26)
  - Deputy Mayor. Speech: "John Lindsay and the Urban Adventure", 1966 April 18 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    Remarks before the Manhattan Chapter of the Brandeis University National Women's Committee, Waldorf-Astoria.
  - Deputy Mayor. Speech: Statement before the United States Senate Subcommittee on Antitrust and Monopoly (Quinine), 1966 May 16 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    In 1966 the U.S. Senate Subcommittee on Antitrust and Monopoly began an investigation into what it called "a fantastic rise" in the price of quinine after members of Congress received numerous complaints from constituents who used quindine, a quinine derivative prescribed for irregular heartbeats. Although he was then Deputy Mayor of New York City, Robert Price was called to testify before the subcommittee because his law firm, Kupferman & Price, was general counsel in 1961–1962 to a small public company, Hexagon Laboratories, Inc., which had sought to obtain surplus United States quinine. At the same time, Dutch interests had bought most of the surplus for 20 cents an ounce and were (in 1966) selling it to pharmaceutical companies for $2 an ounce.
  - Deputy Mayor. Speech: "Is City Government Obsolete?", 1966 June 4 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)